mpp.org 2019-04-17

# Privacy Policy

_Last updated: May 25, 2018_

Protecting your privacy is important to the Marijuana Policy Project (MPP). We are committed to keeping your personal information confidential.

  1. [Why We Collect Personal Information](https://www.mpp.org/#why)
  2. [Type of Data Collected](https://www.mpp.org/#type)
  3. [When We Disclose Contact Information](https://www.mpp.org/#disclosure)
  4. [How We Protect Your Personal Information](https://www.mpp.org/#protection)
  5. [Access to Your Personal Information](https://www.mpp.org/#access)
  6. [Our Organizational Commitment ](https://www.mpp.org/#commitment)
  7. [Cookie / Tracking Technology](https://www.mpp.org/#cookies)
  8. [Collection of Information](https://www.mpp.org/#collection)
  9. [Third-Party Advertising Opt-out](https://www.mpp.org/#advertising)
  10. [Credit Card Information](https://www.mpp.org/#creditcard)
  11. [Commitment to Data Security](https://www.mpp.org/#data-security)
  12. [Third-party Service Providers](https://www.mpp.org/#service-providers)

### **1\. WHY WE COLLECT PERSONAL INFORMATION**

MPP collects and uses personal information to provide individuals with news and information regarding MPP. In addition, we use personal information to keep email subscribers up-to-date on the latest marijuana policy news and information we think they’d like to hear about.

### **2\. TYPE OF DATA COLLECTED**

MPP may collect the following information for users upon submitting forms on mpp.org:

  1. Name
  2. Email
  3. Phone number
  4. Address
  5. City
  6. State
  7. Browser information
  8. Other information provided by users

### **3\. WHEN WE DISCLOSE CONTACT INFORMATION**

Except as provided in this policy, MPP will not share any of your personal information at any time with any organization. Given that MPP is the largest marijuana policy reform organization in the United States, we may contact you on behalf of another organization doing work related to ours. These updates will be sent by MPP personnel via MPP’s secure system. Your personal information will only be handled by MPP employees who are knowledgeable of all rules and policies regarding securely handling all information. They will protect your personal information in accordance with MPP’s Privacy Policy.

MPP occasionally allows other organizations to send mail to individuals on its lists. In these cases, lists containing only names and addresses (no contribution data or other personal information) are delivered to a third-party mailing house for one-time use for that organization’s mailing. To request that we never allow your contact information to be used even in this secure manner, please contact [ **membership@mpp.org**](mailto:membership@mpp.org). If possible, please include your full name, postal address, phone number, and the email address at which you receive messages from MPP.

MPP is dedicated to providing a safe and secure environment for your personal information.

### **4\. HOW WE PROTECT YOUR PERSONAL INFORMATION**

MPP safeguards the security of the data you send us with physical, electronic, and managerial procedures. We urge you to take every precaution to protect your personal data when you are on the internet.

MPP uses industry-standard Secure Sockets Layer (SSL) encryption on all webpages where donations are submitted. To make donations to MPP or organizations supported by MPP, you must use an SSL-enabled browser. (Any current version of Firefox, Chrome, Internet Explorer, or Safari will work.) This protects the confidentiality of your personal and credit card information while it is transmitted over the internet.

### **5\. ACCESS TO YOUR PERSONAL INFORMATION**

If you would like your personal information updated, modified, or removed, you can contact [ **membership@mpp.org**](mailto:membership@mpp.org) with your request. If possible, please include your full name, postal address, phone number, and the email address at which you receive messages from MPP.

#### Third-Party Vendors

Salsa is a third-party data processor which handles data, including personally identifiable information. You can update subscriptions and your profile information with their [Profile Manager](https://salsa4.salsalabs.com/o/51609/profile/).

### **6\. OUR ORGANIZATIONAL COMMITMENT TO PRIVACY**

MPP does not knowingly solicit personal information from children or send them requests for personal information.

MPP’s website contains limited links to other sites. MPP does not share your personal information with those sites, nor is MPP responsible for their privacy practices. We encourage you to learn about the privacy policies of those organizations.

If we are going to use your personal information differently from what is stated here, we will try to contact you via email using the most recent information we have. If you have not given us permission to communicate with you, you will not be contacted, nor will we use your personal information in a new manner.

### **7\. COOKIE/TRACKING TECHNOLOGY**

This site uses cookie and tracking technology. The cookies are useful for gathering information such as browser type and operating system, tracking the number of visitors to the site, and understanding how visitors use the site. If you have enabled the Do Not Track feature of your browser on Internet Explorer, Firefox, Safari, or Chrome, the site’s cookie tracking technology will be disabled.

#### **Necessary Cookies**

Category | Cookie | Description | Expiration  
---|---|---|---  
Cloudflare, Inc. is a U.S. company that provides content delivery network services, DDoS mitigation, Internet security and distributed domain name server services, sitting between the visitor and the Cloudflare user's hosting provider, acting as a reverse proxy for websites. | __cfduid | This cookie is used to identify individual clients behind a shared IP address and apply security settings on a per-client basis. | 1 yr  
  
#### **Performance Cookies**

Category | Cookie | Description | Expiration  
---|---|---|---  
Google Analytics lets us measure site performance by tracking visits and page views. | __ga | Used to distinguish users. | 2 yrs  
__gid | Used to distinguish users. | 24 hrs  
__utma | Used to distinguish users and sessions. The cookie is created when the javascript library executes and no existing __utma cookies exists. The cookie is updated every time data is sent to Google Analytics. | 2 yrs  
__utmc | Not used in ga.js. Set for interoperability with urchin.js. Historically, this cookie operated in conjunction with the __utmb cookie to determine whether the user was in a new session/visit. | End of browser session  
__utmz | Stores the traffic source or campaign that explains how the user reached your site. The cookie is created when the javascript library executes and is updated every time data is sent to Google Analytics. | 6 mos  
__utmt | Used to throttle request rate. | 10 mins  
__utmb | Used to determine new sessions/visits. The cookie is created when the javascript library executes and no existing __utmb cookies exists. The cookie is updated every time data is sent to Google Analytics. | 30 mins  
  
### **8\. COLLECTION OF INFORMATION**

MPP collects personally identifiable information, like names, postal addresses, email addresses, etc., when voluntarily submitted by our visitors. The information you provide is used to fulfill your specific request. Personal information submitted when donating to MPP, MPP Foundation, the MPP PAC, or subscribing to MPP email alerts will not be shared with other groups, but MPP may occasionally allow like-minded organizations to send mailings to you, whereby MPP doesn’t actually share your contact info with these like-minded organizations.

We use third-party advertising companies to serve advertisements when you visit our website. These companies may use aggregated (not personal identifying) information about your visits to this website in order to provide advertisements about goods and services that may be of interest to you. ** ** These companies may also use cookies on our site for advertising purposes on our and other sites.

### **9\. THIRD-PARTY ADVERTISING COOKIES OPT-OUT**

We are dedicated to providing privacy on the internet. In addition to developing our privacy policy, we have provided you the opportunity to opt out of future third-party advertising cookies.

These terms do not cover the collection methods or use of the information collected by these vendors. These vendors have their own privacy policies and may be members of the [Network Advertising Initiative](https://www.networkadvertising.org/) (“NAI”).  To remove yourself from some or all NAI member advertising programs, please visit the [NAI Opt-Out Page](https://www.networkadvertising.org/managing/opt_out.asp) and follow the relevant instructions.  Please note that if you delete, block, or otherwise restrict cookies, or if you use a different computer or internet browser, you may need to renew your opt-out choice.

### **10\. CREDIT CARD INFORMATION**

Credit card numbers are not stored by us. They are submitted directly to a secure third-party vendor for processing.

### **11\. COMMITMENT TO DATA SECURITY**

Your personally identifiable information is kept secure. Only authorized employees and vendors (who have agreed to keep information secure and confidential) have access to this information. All emails and newsletters from this site allow you to opt out of further mailings.

### **12\. THIRD-PARTY SERVICE PROVIDERS**

Portions of the mpp.org site (donation processing, the MPP store, and action center) are operated by a third-party grassroots campaign service provider, which is currently Salsa. Salsa may place cookies on your computer in order to store information, such as items placed in your shopping cart in the MPP store or storing your account login when using the action center. Salsa logs standard technical information, such as the numerical internet protocol (IP) address of the computer you are using; the browser software you use and your operating system; the date and time you access our site; and the internet address of the website from which you linked directly to our site.

Salsa also stores and organizes the personal information collected through this site on our behalf.

From time to time, MPP may work with third-party consultants or other service providers who have access to personally identifiable information. In such cases, we will restrict their use of personally identifiable information in accordance with their assigned tasks and subject to the limitations of this privacy policy.
